<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An ansvver to the ten counter demands propounded by T. Drakes, Preacher of the Word at H. and D. in the county of Essex. By Will. Euring</title>
            <author>Euring, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B13489</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10567</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114521</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849746</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849746</idno>
            <idno type="VID">177088</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B13489)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177088)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 787:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An ansvver to the ten counter demands propounded by T. Drakes, Preacher of the Word at H. and D. in the county of Essex. By Will. Euring</title>
                  <author>Euring, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>W. Brewster],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Leiden :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare 1619.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication date and printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Answers STC 7186a: Draxe, Thomas.  Anterōtēmata Thomæ Draks. Ten counter-demaunds propounded to those of the separation, (or English Donatists) to be directly, and distinctly answered.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Dr. Williams's Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Draxe, Thomas, d. 1618. --  Anterōtēmata Thomæ Draks. Ten counter-demaunds propounded to those of the separation, (or English Donatists) to be directly, and distinctly answered.</term>
               <term>Brownists --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:177088:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177088:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSVVER TO THE TEN COVNTER DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MANDS PROPOVNDED BY T. DRAKES Preacher of <hi>the Word at</hi> H. <hi>and</hi> D. in the County of ESSEX.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Wil. Euring.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PROV. 9.12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>If thou be wiſe thou ſhalt be wiſe for thy ſelfe, and if thou be a ſcorner thou alone ſhalt ſuffer.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the yeare 1619.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:177088:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177088:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the manner of ſome quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relſome perſons, that being beaten by one aduerſarie, too ſtrong for them, they are not quiet in their mindes till they haue got another, with whom they hope to deale well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough; and to beate the former upon his back, wrecking upon him all that anger which they haue harboured in their heart againſt the other, but could not utter as they deſired. So it ſeemes to be with this man: who having had of late (as it is reported) much comba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with the <hi>Morris-dauncing-Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Athieſts</hi> in his pariſh, whereof lately hee was Miniſter: And finding them too hard for him; and that inſteed of being ſheep to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him, they came with open mouth like wolues both againſt the ſheep and Shepheard: he hath thought it beſt, ſeeing theſe wolues thus comming to ſaue himſelfe by flying to an other place; leaving the pore ſheepe in the ſame fould with the wolues, to ſhift for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues as they could. But not reſting ſo, hee hath bethought him of an other ſort of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, with whom he hopes more eaſily to deale: and theſe are the poore <hi>Separatiſts;</hi> againſt whom he hath alſo thoſe <hi>Morris-daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:177088:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>and many greater then they to take his part. Them he encountreth ſtoutly with <hi>Ten Counter-Demands</hi> (as he cals them) with which as with ſo many yron hornes, he hopes ſo to ſhake the ſilly Separatiſts, as not to leaue them a whole bone in their skin. But why doth he call them <hi>Counter-Demands?</hi> Not becauſe he hath anſwered, but onely ſeen, as I heare, 7 <hi>Demands</hi> of theirs, ſome good ſpace ſince pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Theſe he ſhould rather haue anſwered, in my judgment, if he could, for the defence of his Church Communion, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, Miniſterie, and Worſhippe. But it ſeemes he had rather aſke, then anſwer que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions (as what bungler cannot better ſtrike then fence?) and ſo his meaning is, to ſet theſe his <hi>Ten Counter-demands</hi> againſt their <hi>Seaven Demands,</hi> that ſo they might knock heads to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, to ſee whoſe is hardeſt. Since then it muſt be ſo, I will firſt ſet downe thoſe <hi>Seaven,</hi> and after anſwer his <hi>Ten,</hi> ſimply, without all doubt, yet as well as I can: but plainly, and diſtinctly as he deſireth: Intreating thee, good Reader, to beare with my vnſchollerſhip, for I haue not been brought up among the Muſes, but Mariners: and am unwillingly, though par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, drawn hereunto by his importunity.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 1 <hi>Whether the Lord Ieſus Christ haue in his laſt will &amp; Teſtament given unto, and ſet in his Church, ſufficient ordinary Offices, with their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, workes, and maintenance, for the adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his holy things; and for the ordinary in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, guidance, and ſervice of his Church to the end of the world, or no?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Whether the Offices of</hi> Paſtors, Teachers,
<pb facs="tcp:177088:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>Elders, Deacons, <hi>and</hi> Helpers <hi>be thoſe offices ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed in the Teſtament of Chriſt? or whether the preſent eccleſiaſticall offices of</hi> Arch-Biſhops. Lord-Biſhops, Suffragans, Deanes, Prieſts, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cars,, Arch-Deacons, Prebendaries, Canons, Goſpellers, Petty-Canons, Epiſtlers, Virge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, Queriſters, Organ-Players, Parſons, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, Chancelors, Commiſſaries, Proctors, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſters, Appariters <hi>or</hi> Sumners, Churchwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, Doctors of Divinity, Queſtmen <hi>or</hi> Side<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Deacons <hi>or</hi> halfe Prieſts, Chaplins <hi>or</hi> houſe-Prieſts, Clarkes, Sextons, <hi>and the reſt now had and retained in the Cathedrall and Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhionall Aſſemblies of the Land, be thoſe Offices appointed in Chriſts laſt will and teſtament, or no?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Whether the calling, and entrance into the ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall offices laſt before named, with their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministrations, and maintenance now had and retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in England, be the manner of calling, admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, and maintenance, which Chriſt hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted for the offices of his Church, or no?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>Whether every true Church of Chriſt, be not a company of people called and ſeparated out from the world and falſe worſhip and waies thereof, by the word of God, and ioyned together in the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip of the Goſpell, by voluntary profeſſion of the faith, and obedience of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5 <hi>Whether the ſacraments, being ſeales of the righteouſnes which is by faith, may be adminiſtred vnto any other, but to the faithfull and their ſeed, or in any other miniſtery or manner then is preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, and appointed by Ieſus Chriſt the Apoſtle and high preiſt of our profeſſion? And whether they be not otherwiſe adminiſtred in the pariſh aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies of England at this day, or no?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb facs="tcp:177088:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> 6 <hi>Whether the booke of Common prayer, with the feaſts, faſts, ſtinted prayers, holly dayes, and leiturgy preſcribed therein &amp; vſed in the aſſemblies, bee the true worſhip of God commanded in his word, or the deviſe and invention of man for Gods worſhip and ſervice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7 <hi>Whether all people and Churches without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, be not bound in religion, onely to receiue and ſubmit vnto that Ministry, worſhip and order, which Chriſt as Lord and King hath given vnto, and appoynted in his Church: or whether any may receiue and ioyne vnto another deviſed by man for the worſhip and ſervice of God: and conſequently whether they that ioyne to the preſent Eccleſiaſticall ministry, worſhip, and order of the Cathedrall and Pariſhionall Aſſemblies, can be aſſured by the word of God, that they ioyne to the former, or dayned by Chriſt, and not to the latter, deviſed by man for the worſhip and ſervice of God.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:177088:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>AN ANSWERE TO TEN Counter-Demands, Propounded <hi>by</hi> T. DRAKES, <hi>Preacher of</hi> the Word at <hi>H.</hi> and <hi>D.</hi> in the County of ESSEX.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Everend ſir, you haue given vs heer a <hi>Counter blow:</hi> and as it is reported, you yet thinke to giue vs, if not a greater, yet another <hi>Blow,</hi> but you earneſtly deſired to haue theſe your <hi>Ten Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blowes</hi> directly and diſtinctly anſvvered; vvhich I vvill labour to do God aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting mee.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Demand</hi> 1. Your firſt Demande is, <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our ſeperation from your Church or Church-aſſembles of England, can in any probability be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vnto God, ſeeing it hath had (ſay you) ſuch vnhappy beginnings, and ſo many diſmall and fatall events: the firſt founder of it comming to</hi> Iudas <hi>his ſhamefull and fearfull end, hanging him ſelfe: and the ſecond (you ſay) totally recanting and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming againe to you: as divers of our proſelites doe daily, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwere.</head>
               <p>This is the ſume or ground of your firſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mande
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:177088:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>other vvords there are, here and there dropt from your pen, vvhich giue no ſtrength at all to your demand, &amp; therefore I paſſe them by, and anſvver, yea. Though this be true that you haue ſaide, yet may our ſeparation from your Church or pariſh-aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blies of England be pleaſing vnto God: and for proof hereof conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vvhat follovveth.</p>
               <p>This your demand is like as if a Cananite or Philiſtim ſhould thus haue demaunded of the Iſraelites. Whether is it like that the wars you hould againſt vs, can in any probability be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing unto God, ſeeing that they haue had ſuch vnhappy ſucceſſe, vvith ſo many diſmal &amp; fatall events? ſome vvere burnt vvith fyre, Nom. 11.1 ſome ſunke into the earth aliue, Nom. 16.32.33 ſome vvere deſtroyed of ſerpents. Nom. 21.6. ſome by the enemyes ſvvord. Nom. 14.45. ſome by the ſvvord of their own brethren. Exod. 32 27. Euen <hi>Moſes</hi> &amp; <hi>Aaron,</hi> your firſt &amp; greateſt, yea principall pillars of greateſt reckoning, died in the deſert for their ſin. And of ſixe hundred thouſand men that came out of <hi>Egipt</hi> to fight againſt us, Exod. 12.37. onely two men are left aliue. Nom. 26.64, 65 &amp;c. What think you Sir? Was this vvarre in any probability pleaſing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God? if you ſay yea, you haue anſvvered your demande your ſelfe: and diſcovered your ovvne folly: for thus you ſee a Pagan might haue pleaded againſt Iſraell, Gods true Church then, vvith as much collour and more truth, then you that are called a Chriſtian, can doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us novv: and thus I thinke your firſt demande is ſufficiently anſvvered.</p>
               <p>But it may be ſir, you vvill not be thus ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfied,
<pb facs="tcp:177088:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>vvithout your particulars be examined. <hi>M. Bolton,</hi> vvhich (you ſay) vvas the firſt founder of our ſeparation, hanged himſelf, as did <hi>Iudas:</hi> vvell. Proue you as much for <hi>Boi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> as I doe for <hi>Iudas.</hi> As vve deny <hi>Bolton</hi> to haue been the firſt founder of our ſeparation, ſo ſure I am, that <hi>Iudas</hi> vvas one of the firſt and principalleſt publiſhers of the goſpell of Chriſt: for he vvas numbered vvith the Apoſtles, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one of the tvvelue and had received fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovvſhip in their miniſtration, Act. 1.17.</p>
               <p>And vvill you novv therefore call the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell and Chriſtianity into queſtion, as whether it be of God or no? becauſe this <hi>Iudas</hi> hanged himſelfe: if no, vvhat vvaight then is in your demand? And novv I pray you ſir conſider alſo that this <hi>M. Bolto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> one of the Elders of that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated Church vvhere of <hi>M. Fits</hi> vvas paſtor in the beginning of <hi>Queene Elizabeths</hi> raigne, firſt revolted at <hi>Pauls Croſſe,</hi> falling back again to you: and vvas reproved &amp; excommunicated for this, by that ſeparated Church: and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, not haveing grace to returne or repent hanged himſelfe. This being ſo <hi>M. Boltons</hi> martyrdom is little for the credit of your cauſe, or Church, whereof he dyed a member.</p>
               <p>The ſecond you ſay totally recanted &amp;c. And this you note to bee <hi>Browne.</hi> And ſay I, ſo did <hi>Demas.</hi> 2. Tim. 4.10. vvhich ſometime vvas a fellow-helper with <hi>Paul</hi> as vvell as <hi>Luke</hi> Col. 4.14. Phil. 2.4. As divers others in all ages haue done, vvho loved this preſent vvorld more then God. Can it not therefore ſtand vvith your liking Sir, that the Goſpell vvhich Chriſt or <hi>Paul</hi> preached, can in any probability bee
<pb facs="tcp:177088:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>pleaſing unto God, becauſe <hi>Iudas</hi> hanged him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and <hi>Demas</hi> totally recanted it. I pray you Sir conſider vvhat the Apoſtle ſaith; <hi>What though ſome haue not beleeved or been unfaithfull, ſhall their unfaithfulneſſe, make the faith of God without effect? God forbid. Rom.</hi> 3.3.4.</p>
               <p>And againe, conſider I pray you: Chriſtian religion vvas at a lovv ebb vvhen ſo many went back from Chriſt, that hee ſaid to the twelue, <hi>will yee alſo leaue me.</hi> Ioh. 6.66. yet you ſee ſtill Chriſtianity florisheth: and wee, to our exceeding great comfort do behold it. And for us, though many bad ones haue gon a way, yet God bringeth better in their place dayly. And thus I thinke your firſt Demande is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly and diſtinctly anſvvered, as you deſire. Onely this I will further add concerning M. <hi>Browne,</hi> that he hath ſo left it in practiſe, as to ſhew the corruption of his heart; yet ſo hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth it in profeſſed iudgement, as ſhevvs the ſtrength of the truth, ſtil upholding it ſelf in ſo evil a conſcience: who profeſſeth in keeping his Miniſtry, that he <hi>liveth of the ſpoiles of Babylon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And for Maſter <hi>Boulton,</hi> although you think you haue great advantage againſt us in his caſe &amp; ſome others, who haue faln from us: yet if things be rightly conſidered, the contrary vvill appeare. And as <hi>Abimelech</hi> king of <hi>Gerar,</hi> vvhen he reproued <hi>Abraham</hi> for denying <hi>Sarah</hi> to be his vvife, had more need to haue reproued him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for his want of the feare of God, &amp; of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon humanity, by vvhich pore <hi>Abraham</hi> was driven to that ſtrayt: ſo you, in upbraiding us with theſe mens fals, had more need reproue your ſelves, &amp; your ovvn moſt unmercifull dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings
<pb facs="tcp:177088:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>towards us, by which divers are forced to deny the truth as <hi>Abraham</hi> did his vvife, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their conſciences: vvhereuppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth moſt fearefull diſpayre &amp; ſometimes ſuch wofull events as this vpon <hi>Boltons</hi> Apoſtacie was; &amp; ſo you are before the Lord, made guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty both of the bloud of the bodies, &amp; of the ſoules of thoſe miſerable men.</p>
               <p>And whereas you haue a marginall note of one M. <hi>Nowel</hi> in <hi>Warwick-ſhire;</hi> you are the firſt from whom I ever heard any thing of that man, and therefore this is all that I can ſay, If hee vvere not fully perſwaded of the truth in that eſtate vvherein he ſtood, but dyed vvith a troubled mind ſeeking the truth: vvhat doth this make ether againſt us, or for you? I ſee nothing, let vviſe men judge &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Demand.</hi> Your ſecond demand is, as I vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it. <hi>Whether our profeſſion, religion, and diſcipline, as it ſtandeth in oppoſition to your Pariſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſembles in</hi> England <hi>and the reſt of the reformed Churches, can be of God, or haue any approbation from God: ſeeing that it hath no vertue, power, and efficacy in it, (as the Goſpel preached in your pariſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſemples through Gods bleſſings aboundantly hath) to win, convert, and draw vnto our party, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, Atheists, Papiſts, Heretiks, rude, profane &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Anſwer.</hi> To this your demand I anſwere yea: our profeſſion religion and diſcipline (as you call it) may be of God, and haue approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God, though not converting any ſuch. And if it be ſo of God, as it be approved in his word, it is enough, though we haue not converted any at all; and for proofe hereof, as
<pb facs="tcp:177088:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>alſo for further anſvver to your demand, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider this that follovveth.</p>
               <p>Your demand is like as if a Cananite ſhould thus haue demaunded of <hi>Noah.</hi> Gen. 6. Can this thy Arke building, be of God, or haue any approbation from God, ſeeing that in all this time there appeareth neither vertue, povver, nor efficacie to vvin, convert, and dravv vnto thy party any at all? for thou canſt hardly ſhevv any one perſon converted vnto thee by thy preaching, or Arke building theſe hundered and tvventy yeers? vvhat thinke you Sir? <hi>could</hi> Noah <hi>his Arke building be of God, or haue any, &amp;c</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alſo, I pray you Sir conſider vvith your ſelfe vvhat anſvver you vvould haue made, if any of your Morriſ-dancing papiſts or prophane Atheiſts (vvith whom you, but lately, vvere much cumbered) ſhould haue demanded the lyke of you? Your adminiſtration, and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſteriall office, had ſo little vertue, povver, and efficacy in it, among them, that you were glad to leaue them vnconverted &amp; come away from them: and it may be, they deemed your miniſtry not to be of God, nor to haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny approbation from God: and you your ſelfe alſo peradventure, thinking the ſame thing, and ſeeing alſo that thoſe to vvhom you ſued for redreſſe, could not or vvould not giue any more <hi>vertue, power, or efficacy to your Ministry,</hi> and office, you tooke the beſt courſe, as you thought, even to leaue them in their Idolatry and prophanes and come avvay from them: for the vvhich I vvould haue you minde vvell and conſider vvhat the Lord ſaith. Zacha. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.17.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:177088:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſurely ſir, ſeeing that you thus deeme of things by the effects, you can not but thinke very hardly of your ſelfe: conſidering the ſmall effect your miniſtry hath vvrought, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially amongſt your Morriſ-dauncers.</p>
               <p>And yet for further anſvver to your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, conſider ſir, vve are a poore vveak diſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed people here in England, hated and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of all, or the moſt part in the lande: and therefore, if vve haue any meetings or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming together on the Lords day? they muſt be very private for feare of ſuch perſecuting ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries as cannot indure (and are ignorant of) the truth of Gods ordinances to be taught and practiſed, ſo that Papiſts, Atheiſts, and ſuch like profane, come not at our exerciſes: and hovv is it poſſible vve ſhould convert any that come not to heare vs? If vve ſhould demand of you, how many Turks and Saracens haue been converted in your Pariſh aſſemblies, vvhat an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſvver vvould you giue vs, that vvill not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſvver your ſelfe.</p>
               <p n="2">2 To let paſſe the Churches in this vvay, beyond the ſeas, vvhich haue their more free meetings, and able miniſteries, and vvhere this bleſſing of God in converting men, is more ſeen, then, I think, in any of the Pariſhes that ever you your ſelfe vvere miniſter of (though you haue beene in more then a good many or then a good Paſtour should or vvould be) I may bouloly ſay, that we, hovv fevv or meane ſoever vvee are; do convert more to our Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches thou you do to yours. All theſe Atheiſts, Heretickes, and prophaine perſons vvere as vvell of your Church before their converſion,
<pb facs="tcp:177088:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:177088:8"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:177088:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>as after: and for the Papiſts, eyther they come to hear you, and then they are of your Church alſo, namely Church-Papiſts, or not: and then, hovv doe you convert them by your miniſtry. Beſides, it is evident, that the number of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts do dayly increaſe in the land infinitely; ſuch is your plentifull converſion of Papiſts.</p>
               <p>But indeede Sir, your follovving vvords, vvherein you pleaſe to terme vs, <hi>refined refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, ſaying, that we ſeduce only the ſound, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert and eſtrange from you thoſe that are otherwiſe well affected, &amp; of ſom vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding &amp;c.</hi> are worth the conſidering: and I intreat the Godly rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to take knovvledg of this that follovveth.</p>
               <p>Firſt I profeſſe vnfainedly vvith an vpright heart as in Gods preſence, vvho knovveth the ſecrets of all hearts: that neither I my ſelfe, nor any other (to my knowledg) that profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the ſame courſe of true religion vvith me) did ever intend or once conceiue, ſo much as in thought, any one poynt or parte of ſedition, or evill conſpiracie, againſt any mans perſon: much leſſe againſt the kings maieſty his royall ſtate, &amp; government: but vve do acknowledge his maieſty to be ſupreme governour in all his dominions in all cauſes and over all perſons of vvhat eſtate or degree ſo ever they be: and that no perſon may declyne or appeall from his authotity or iudgment in any cauſe vvhat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever: but that in all things obedience is due vnto him, eyther Actiue if the thing comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded be not againſt Gods vvord, or Paſſiue if it be: except pardon can be obtained: and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto vvee doe diligently exhorte and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke all men at all times &amp;c.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177088:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> This being in the firſt place conſidered, it is true that you ſay: our cauſe hath vvrought moſt vppon ſuch as haue ſome vnderſtanding and knovvledg; and are of tender conſciences plyable to the truth: others of more corrupt conſciences haue ſet againſt us, and againſt our cauſe, and blaſphemed it &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The conſideration of this, will in any wiſe mans iudgment rather lead vnto our cauſe, then from it, when the better ſort, by your owne confeſſion, doe come to vs, the worſer and baſer ſorte remayne ſtill with you. And this much for anſwer to your ſecond demand, novv to your third.</p>
               <p>This your third demand is of another kinde differing from the former: for here you ſeeme to leaue your nationall Church and Parish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſembles of England, and make your demand only for your reformed aſſemblies: wherein you ſay the Goſpell is ſincerely preached and profeſſed, and the ſacraments duly admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred &amp;c. But of this particular you shall haue anſvver vvhen I come to your 7 and 8 demand?</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Demand.</hi> Your demand is here to know. <hi>Whether thoſe reformed Aſſemblies whereof you ſpeake are worſe then the Iewes Sinagogues: and your miniſters worſe then the Scribes and phariſes which ſat in</hi> Moſes <hi>Chayer? Whom Chriſt comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the people to heare &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>Anſw.</hi> Your demand then being onely in deſence of your reformed Aſſemblies, it had been vvell, if you had shevved us vvhere and vvhich thoſe aſſemblies be, that are reformed. Wee knovv indeed, that many amongſt you both miniſters and people haue made much
<pb facs="tcp:177088:10"/>ſuite to Parliaments, and vvrote many bookes (of vvhich I haue read ſome) for reformation of your Church and Miniſtery: but ſtill to the beſt of our diſcerning, all your pariſh aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies are as before vnder one and the ſame or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and maner of vvorſhippe miniſterie, and confuſion of people: all governed by the fame ſpirituall laws, &amp; ſpirituall Lords, their ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all courts, and canons: all being ſtil one Church, all one communion and fellovvshippe: ſo that your Demand being onely for your reformed aſſemblies, and yet you tell us not which nor vvhere they be, how can vvee giue you a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect anſvver to your demand.</p>
               <p>Firſt therefore tell us vvhere and vvhich thoſe aſſembles be that are reformed, &amp; then you shall haue a direct anſvver, God vvilling. In the meane time vve vvill take this for one advantage among the reſt: that is, that there appeareth a checke in your conſcience, becauſe you make your defence, or demand but for a part of your Church: that is, your reformed aſſemblies: vvhereby you intimate, that there is a vvorſer ſort of aſſemblies, that are vnrefor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, vvhich you vvill not pleade for: vvhere as if your Church or Church-aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blies of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land vvere Chriſts true Church, vve thinke you ſhould haue labored to defend the vvhole: is not every one of Chriſts true Churches to be defended? hovv deceitfully then doe you deale vvith your Church that ſeeke to vphould your reformed aſſembles and neglect the reſt: all being in one brotherhood and communion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,</p>
               <p>But it may be ſir, you are driven to ſhift for
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:177088:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>your ſelfe: therefore if you vvill ſhevv vs vvhich be your reformed aſſembiles, vve will ſhevv you great difference betvveen thoſe Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogues of the Ievves, vvhere Chriſt and his diſciples did teach, and your pariſh aſſemblies: great difference betvvene thoſe that ſat in <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> Chayre, vvhich vvere in true office vnder <hi>Moſes</hi> according to the lavv, and you, vvith the reſt, that haue no true office vnder Chriſt according to the goſpell. Your mighty reaſon <hi>a minore ad majus</hi> (which words indeed I vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not) is this: If (ſay you) our Lord Ieſus, his diſciples and people, did not ſeparate from thire Sinagogues and aſſemblies, that vvere in faith and maners more defectiue then ours are: much leſſe ought they to ſeparate from our aſſembles, vvherein all the grounds of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian religion are ſoundly held and profeſſed, (you might haue added) and but fevv pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, neither of preiſts nor people, in vvhom couetouſnes, vvrath, enuie, and contention doe daily abound: many thouſands neither know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, nor regarding to knovv vvhat true faith meaneth: and for their manners vvhich you vvould ſeeme ſo much to commend: let the manners even of that Pariſh aſſembly vvhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in your ſelfe did of late exerciſe your ſpirituall authority in vain: as alſo the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nerly conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and converſation of almoſt all in generall, teſtifie hovv true this your bold affirmation of their manners is: and vvithall, let the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders minde, that although you boaſt of all the grounds of chriſtian religion, yet it is but <hi>held and profeſſed;</hi> not practiſed among you: ſo that it may ſeeme you beleeue alſo, that to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:177088:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>hould and profeſſe, (vvithout obedience) is ſufficient for the ſalvation of the profeſſors: but to the intent that this may be better diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, I doe intreat and deſire all that are chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianly minded to reade and conſider of theſe fevv places of ſcripture. Iam. 1.21.22.25.26. Tit. 1.16.2. Theſ. 1.7.8.9. Eze. 22.26 I vvill only poynt the places, let the godly reade and iudge.</p>
               <p n="4">4 <hi>Demand</hi> Novv to your fourth demand, vvhich is; <hi>Whether thoſe great multituds of people ſpoken of Math.</hi> 14.13.14.15. <hi>&amp;c. Ioh.</hi> 6.5.10.11. <hi>can with any reaſon be denyed to be mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the viſible church, though yet wanting the pretended conſtitution of the Separatiſts? and albeit many of them (you ſay) were drawne, not by do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine but by miracles, report, and with their deſire to be fed: &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4 <hi>Anſw.</hi> To this your demand I anſvver directly, yea: they may vvith good reaſon grounded on the word of God (ſpeaking as you doe of the multitude) be denyed to be members of any viſible Church, and this doth plainely apeare in the ſame 2 chapters; namely, Mat. 14. Ioh. 6. which may alſo be compared with other ſcriptures to proue the ſame.</p>
               <p>There were none of them members of the viſible Church of Chriſt, but thoſe that did viſibly appeare to be Chriſts Diſciples: but the multitude that followed him for their bellies ſake were not his Diſciples, as the very words of the text doe proue; where a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence is put betweene the one and the other. Firſt, looke Mat. 14.19. where it is ſaid, <hi>Hee cauſed the multitude to ſit downe, and when he had
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:177088:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>bleſſed, &amp; broke, he gaue it to the diſciples &amp; the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples to the multitude. And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they had all eaten &amp; were ſufficed, he cauſed his diſciples to enter into a ſhip while he ſent the multitude away.</hi> Mat. 14.22.23. Mar. 4.4. If you ſay, he taught them alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; it is true: yet was it in parables: and afterward he expounded all things to his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples aparte. Mar. 4.10.11.34.35.36. Mat. 13.10.11.13.14.15.36.</p>
               <p>And thus it doth plainly appear that the multitude were not his diſciples: and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, not members of any viſible Church of Chriſt: for then he would not haue ſent them away empty in their ſoules, and full in their bodyes, but he would haue expounded all things to them altogether, for their edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and further comfort. But the text doth plainly shevv the diſciples to be vvithin: and the multitude to be without. Mar. 4.10.11.12.</p>
               <p>And whereas you further demand, <hi>Whether thoſe</hi> 3. <hi>thouſand in the ſecond of the acts, that were converted at</hi> Peters <hi>Sermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, were not true me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of a true viſible Church before they had officers choſen among them? &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I Anſvver yea, they were: this you ſay can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee refuted; and it is true: but what haue you gained by this? what doth this helpe the multitude ſpoken of before? If I should charge you here with deceitfull dealing, by shuffling this place of the Acts with the other tvvo places of ſcripture, therby to make your demand ſeem ſomething, and of ſome weight, blinding therewith the eies of your readers; I doubt you could hardly cleere your ſelfe with
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:177088:12"/>a good conſcience: but howſoever you would ſeeme to ſhuffle them together to ſerue your turne, yet they are plainly diſtinguiſhed thus as followeth,</p>
               <p>This place of the Acts, ſpeaketh of three thouſand godly penitent ſinners, pricked in their hearts for their ſins, and converted at that ſermon: the multitude ſpoken of in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two ſcriptures were not ſuch, by your owne grant. Againe, theſe in the ſecond of the Acts received the apoſtles doctrine gladly, and forſaking that froward generation with whom they lived, they ioyned them ſelues vnto the Church, as appearath in the 37.40. and 41. verſes. Now who can deny theſe 3. thouſand (though ſtill the multitude be denied) to be members of the true viſible Church when the text ſaith they were <hi>added to the Church?</hi> although it ſhould be granted, that as yet they had no other officers choſen but the Apoſtles. But then ſay you, <hi>And why not our Church-aſſemblies in England, (much more groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the faith) a true viſible Church. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſvver no, it vvill not follovv; becauſe (howſoever ſome fevv of yovv may be more grounded in knovvledge of the truth then they vvere, and thereby your ſins and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions much more greater againſt God, by knovving more, and obaying leſſe) your par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh aſſemblies vvere not at the firſt gathred from others by the preaching of the vvord, their hearts being touched vvith godly ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rovv for their ſins, neither do they yet ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to be pricked in their hearts for their ſins, as thoſe three thouſand vvere. Your pariſh
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:177088:12"/>aſſemblies do not gladly receiue the Apoſtles doctrine, and continue therein, vvith gladnes of heart to be directed, and ordered thereby, as they did: but every man among you, vvill doe vvhat his owne heart liſteth: euen according to the frowardnes and anger of his euill heart: ſo that vvere it not for the lavves of the nation and the power of the magiſtrates reſtrayning them more then the doctrine of Chriſt and the Apoſtles; the manifold miſchiefs that would be done by one againſt another among you through the enuie and malice of your euill and wicked hearts, is too manifeſt to be denyed, and too ſhamefull to be defended. I do hartely deſire you, Sir, to examine your own heart well in this point, &amp; minde well the exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that the Apoſtle giveth in Heb. 3.12. 2. Cor. 13.5.6.7.8.9.11. 1. Cor. 11.28.29.30.31. you ſee and know that your Pariſh-aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies are ſo far from continuing in the Apoſtles doctrine, that they neither konw (therfore not receiue) nor yet regard to know what the wholſome doctrine of the Apoſtles meaneth. I ſpeake not this of all in particular, the Lord knoweth my heart is far from ſo thinking: I know many that haue tender con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and loving affections, and do well regard the beſt rhings: but I ſpeake generally of the conditions of the moſt, with whom the better ſort ſtand all in the communion, and in one order, or diſorder rather: being mingled together all in one brotherhood: and that not by perſonall fayling, but by the very conſtitution and lawes of your Church, civill and eccleſiaſticall, cleane contrary to
<pb facs="tcp:177088:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>the revealed will of God in his Word.</p>
               <p>Even you your ſelf Sir, that are a leader, and profeſſe your ſelfe to be a guide to the blinde, you breake the law of God,, and defile his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things: you put no difference betweene the holy and prophane, neither diſcerne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the vnclean and the cleane, ſo the Lord is prophaned among you. Eze. 22.26. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider I pray you and compare together theſe few places of Scripture Mat. 18.1516.17. Rom. 16.17. 1. Cor. 5.11.12.13. 2, Theſ, 36.7. &amp;c. and then compare this order heere ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by Chriſt, and his apoſtles, vnto the order of your Church and Pariſh-aſſemblies, &amp; you ſhall ſee, even by theſe 5. places of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, how far you are from that holy order which Chriſt in his laſt will and teſtament hath given and appointed vnto his viſible Church to walke in, and to practiſe.</p>
               <p>You compell all that are of your Pariſh (howſoever vnworthie or vnable) to pay their offrings, and to receiue the communion, eſpecially at your holy time of Eaſter: there is the table prepared, bread and wine ſet, come that will and welcom. Eſay, 65.11.12. yea if they be dwelling in your Pariſh, and will not pay their offrings, and come to the communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on daily, they are by you preſented into your ſpirituall Courts, thither they are ſummoned: if they appeare not obedienly, paying their fees, clearing the bookes &amp;c. they ſhall be by that Court excommunicated out of your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh-aſſemblies: and then, before they may be admitted againe either to the fore named ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet, or to your devine ſervice (as you call it)
<pb facs="tcp:177088:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>their purſes muſt pay deere enough for a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, or abſolution, which they muſt receiue humbly kneeling on their knees before Maſ. Commiſſary, or Maſ. Chancellors worſhip: and if they die exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate before they haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived this bounſing bleſſing, they may not be brought into your holy ground to be bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried there in chriſtian buriall, (as you call it) vnleſſe their friends will firſt purchaſe abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for them. If the mould of this came not from Rome, then I pray you Sir, ſhew vs where you learned it: for in the whole Bible, we cannot finde any ſuch ſpirituall order given or appointed by God vnto his Church.</p>
               <p n="5">5 <hi>Demand.</hi> Your 5. demand is <hi>Whether that in</hi> Conſtantines <hi>(the firſt Chriſtian Emperour) tyme, and ever ſince, vnto</hi> M. Iohn Calvins <hi>dayes for the ſpace of</hi> 13 <hi>hundered yeeres there was no Christian Churches in</hi> Aſia, Africke <hi>and</hi> Europe, <hi>becauſe they had the ſame outward conſtitution, formall ſtate, Biſhops, Archbiſhops, Metropolytans, and Church government, for ſubſtance, &amp; ſubſtance of doctrine, that our Engliſh Church hath and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To tell you the truth: I know not well how to anſwere this your demand: yet not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is ſo divinely grounded on the word of God: but only becauſe I want ſcoole lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and knowledge of auncient Authors wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings: as being not able to read and vnderſtand them: ſo that now you haue me at a non plus: as wiſe men and fooles vſe to ſay.</p>
               <p>Yet this is one thing much to be lamented: that a man of your place and learning ſhould leaue the Scripture, the true worde of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb facs="tcp:177088:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>God, and thus inquire of the dead: but according to the ould proverbe, like will to like.</p>
               <p n="5">5 <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Thus much I ſay for anſwer to this your far-fetched demand: I do beleeue and am fully perſwaded by the word of God, that in whatſoever Emperours or Kings time, ſince the time of Chriſt: in what Nation or Country ſoever: whether in Aſia, Africk, Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope, (or whereſoever) any Church or Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches hath been, is, or ſhall be gathered or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted in any other manner, or by and with any other matter, vnder or vnto any other wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, miniſtry, ſpirituall Governours, or ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all government, then the ſame for ſubſtance in manner and matter, which Chriſt and his Apoſtles haue appointed in the new teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: they are not the true viſible Churches of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>I do not meane hereby, an abſolute true and perfect gathering or conſtituting: but that all things, both for the gathering and continuing of the true viſible Church of Chriſt, muſt be (ſo far as can be diſcerned by men) agreable to the word of God, as God ſhall make men able to diſcerne and vnderſtand the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. And this is all that I can ſay for anſwer to this your demand: only I will not looſe the good advantage that I haue gained by the ſame; which is this; I ſee that you are not able to approue your Church by the word of God, and therefore you are driven to make inquiry, and to look about you to ſee if you can eſpie and find out any other Churches, though never ſo far of, whoſe conſtitution or
<pb facs="tcp:177088:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>gathering, miniſtry and worſhip, eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Governors and Eccleſiaſticall government, is for ſubſtance lyke vnto you, hoping by them to iuſtifie your ſelues: but how like it is that other Churches can afoord you any help or ſauegard, when as by the verdict of Gods word you ſtand co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned, let the godly iudge. <hi>Hee hath neede of a ſtaffe that leaneth on a reed.</hi> And yet even for this your poore proof, it is affirmed by ſome, who know thoſe hiſtories, that it is a very boaſt without all truth, that the Churches either in <hi>Conſtantines</hi> time, or a long time after, were gathered by compulſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all, tag and rag, in the empyre, as yours are of all, in the kindome: or that there were any ſuch Arch Biſhops, or Lord Biſhops, with ſole authority to rule and governe. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, let the Reader note how in your very Demand, you do grauut the great difference betweene the Churches ſince <hi>Calvines</hi> time, that is betweene all reformed Churches; and your vnreformed Church of Enland.</p>
               <p n="6">6 <hi>Demand.</hi> Your ſixt Demand is, <hi>Whether the reformed Churches in the lower and higher Germany, in France, the Churches in Geneva, &amp;c. that come neerer to our conſtitution and diſcipline (you ſay) then yours in England do; be true viſible Churches or no? &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this your Demand, you haue added two branches depending vppon the former, the which I will anſwer, as you haue ſet them downe one afer another.</p>
               <p n="6">6 <hi>Anſwer.</hi> I anſwer yea, they are true viſible conſtituted Churches, and haue a true and lawfull miniſtery ſet over them: both which,
<pb facs="tcp:177088:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>you in your Pariſh-aſſemblies want.</p>
               <p>Then you further demand, and ſay. If they be ſuch, why then do not we adjoyn our ſelues to ſome of thoſe, but diſtaſte them (you ſay) as much as wee do yours? I thinke Sir, it had been a poynt of wiſedom firſt to haue heard our anſwer before you had thus haſtily affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that we diſtaſt them as much as we do yours: but <hi>Solomon</hi> hath anſwered you for your haſte, Pro. 29.20. And I will anſwer your Demand.</p>
               <p>I haue in my former anſwer affirmed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be true conſtituted Churches, &amp; that they haue a true &amp; lawful miniſtry ſet over the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: whereby you ſee we do not alltogether diſtaſte them as much as we doe yours. And now to this your Demand; which is: <hi>why we do not adioyne our ſelves vnto them &amp;c.</hi> I think this may ſerue for anſwer: we can not vnderſtand their lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage: and I think you cannot giue vs any good reaſon why we ſhould adioyn our ſelves to worſhip God though in a true Church, when we can not vnderſtand what they ſay: for how ſhould we profit or be edified by their doctrine how ſhould we ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to their giving of thanks, ſeeing we know not what they ſay? 1. Cor. 14.16.17.</p>
               <p>You yet further Demand: <hi>Why we do not in iudgement aſſent vnto any or all thoſe reformed Churches that with a ioynt conſent (as may appeare</hi> (you ſay) <hi>by the harmony of confeſſions) ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knwledge the Church of England to be a true Church, and giue it the right hand of fellowſhip? how dare they</hi> (ſay you) <hi>refuſe? &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this I anſwer: I do not know that the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:177088:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>word of God bindeth vs to aſſent vnto the iudgment of true Churches, any further then we vnderſtand their iudgment to aſſent with (and agree vnto) the word of God.</p>
               <p>True Churches may err in their iudgment of another Church, eſpecially if they be not rightly informed of their eſtate: as it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the reformed Churches are not rightly informed of yours: for how then can they approue of the conſtitution, miniſtry, ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all governours, &amp; ſpirituall governme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of your Church to be warrantable by the word of God, but they muſt in ſo doing condemne themſelues: for in all theſe points they are as far contrary to you, as white and black: true and falſe are the one to the other: and I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe none will ſay that two ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>traries can be both true. But mind with all: the Apoſtle ſaith to perticular Churches and perſons, <hi>iudge ye what I ſay,</hi> 1. Cor. 10.15. <hi>beleeue not every ſpirit, but try the ſpirits &amp;c.</hi> 1, Ioh. 4.1. And againe, <hi>if any man preach otherwiſe vnto you then we haue preached, let him be accurſed.</hi> Gala. 1.8.9.</p>
               <p>Now you ſeeme to teach vs another Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell: for you would not haue vs iudge and try our ſelues and others by the word of God, but ſend to other Churches in <hi>Germany,</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Geneva,</hi> heare what they ſay and what they iudg for truth or falſhood: if they approue, who dare diſalow? if they giue the right hand of fellowſhip, how dare we refuſe? &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Thus you daube with vntempered morter, haueing nothing but ſuch ould popiſh va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour
<pb facs="tcp:177088:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>to countenance your Counter-Demands: doth ill beſeeme a man of your place and learning. Heare what the word of God ſaith, <hi>To the Law and to the Teſtimony: if they ſpeake not according to this word, it is becauſe there is no light in them.</hi> Iſay. 8.20.</p>
               <p>Your leaving of this Law and this <hi>Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> makes vs leaue you: you may as well bid vs put out our owne eyes, that other men may lead vs: and as ſoone will we follow you in that, as in this your popiſh counſell.</p>
               <p>We haue learned to liue by our owne faith, and to know that every man muſt bear his owne burden, and anſwerr for him ſelfe vnto God. Hab. 2.4. Gala. 6.5. And to think that any may excuſe them ſelues, or be the boulder becauſe they haue the approbation of others, when they can not approue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues by the word of God, will proue but an evill and falſe deluſion of Sathan: therefore ſeeing that all men, even whole Churches may erre in their iudgments: let every man take heed how he iudgeth, and how he depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth on other men, and makes fleſh his arme, and will not heare the word of the Lord, that reproveth his iniquities: As for the reformed Churches, we beleeue that they reioyce for the many truthes you witnes againſt Popery, and we alſo do the like: but if you rely vppon their aprobbation, and will not examine your waies, and try your ſelves by the word of God, you may periſh in your ſins, and other churches ſhal not be able to excuſe or ſaue you. And thus I think your ſixt Demand is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently anſwered. <hi>Let him that readeth conſider.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:177088:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> 7 <hi>Demand.</hi> Your 7 and 8 Demands are ſo much alike, that one may iudge them to be twins, they reſemble either other, and ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like the reſt: therfore this anſwer ſhall ſerue for them both vntill further occaſion be offered. In your ſeventh Demand you thus begin. <hi>How can the Church, or Church aſſemblies bee falſe, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7 <hi>Anſwer.</hi> I anſwer, your Church (and Church-aſſemblies) of England may be falſe for ought that you haue yet ſaid to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary: but if we might intreat you to ſet foorth and ſhew vs the right forme and faſhion of the building of your Church, we ſhould the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diſcerne it, and giue you a directer anſwer to your Demand then now we can do: but in the meane time we will a little conſider and examine what you ſay. In theſe words of yours, <hi>how can the Church or Church-aſſemblies &amp;c.</hi> you grant the whole nation to be a Church: then me things you ſeeme to devide that Church into many Churches, calling them <hi>Church Aſſemblies:</hi> meaning thereby (as I coniecture) your Pariſh-aſſemblies.</p>
               <p n="8">8 <hi>Demand.</hi> And ſo it appeareth by your 8 Demand, where you write thus: <hi>How can the formall ſtate (as they call it) of the provinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, dioceſan, cathedrall and Pariſhonall Churches of England, and the regiment thereof be vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, &amp;c,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here you haue foyſted in a word or two which I found not in the former, which word, becauſe I vnderſtand it not, as you (perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture) meane: therefore I will not meddle with it: neither will I meddle with popiſh
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:177088:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>names and titles of your Churches, though you muſter them vp ſo valorouſly as if you ment to terrifie the readers with the very names of them: only this I finde your demand in both, to be: how the Church (and Pariſh-aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies) of England can be falſe; the reſt dropt, or rather ſcattered abroad throughout your De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, is but your vnſavery ſalt, which you haue caſt out vpon the dunghill of your coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter work: all being (as you think) ſo cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched together, as that it cannot be eaſily ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked abroad: but I will try, if by the help of God and the truth of his word, I can ſhew what vnſavery ſtuffe it is.</p>
               <p n="8">8 <hi>Anſw.</hi> To theſe your 7. and 8. Demands I anſwer: that to hould and maintaine a nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall Church: that is to hould, that any na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion can be a church, now in the time of the Goſpell, we deeme to be erroneous and falſe: and do affirme that no warrant or defence for it can be found in the word of God. It is an hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane invention, and differeth from the teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chriſt, which ſheweth many Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to be in a nation or Country: as in <hi>Iudea Aſia, Galatia</hi> &amp;c. Gala. 1.2.22. Rev. 1.4. But not any nation to be a Church.</p>
               <p>Now that yours is a Nationall Church, not only the name and title, as it is vſually called, (beſides your own grant) but the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo ſheweth: for it hath a paſtor over the whole na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the <hi>Archbiſhop of Canterbury, Metropolitan and Primate over all England: your moſt reverend father in God,</hi> who maketh &amp; conſecrateth the <hi>Dioceſian Biſhops,</hi> whereupon ariſeth <hi>Dioceſian Churches or Sees:</hi> and they againe make your
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:177088:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>Pariſh Prieſts, to the Archbiſhops: and to his ſucceſſours the inferiour Biſhops haue ſworne <hi>(So help them God in Ieſus Chriſt)</hi> all due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence and obedience. This your book of conſecration ſheweth: and we deſire you to ſhew vs warrant for thoſe things in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, if you can: or elſe ſhew vs where you haue learned them.</p>
               <p>In your 8 Demand you ſay thus; <hi>The name, calling, and office of theſe Biſhops</hi> (for either you muſt meane theſe Biſhops (or the like) or elſe you ſpeake nothing to the matter in hand) <hi>Whether</hi> (ſay you) <hi>wee reſpect, ordination of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, or power of juriſdiction: is the ſame for ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, expreſſed in the New teſtament. And this</hi> (you ſay) <hi>hath been and will be proved, ſeeing it hath had a continuall ſucceſſion from the Apoſtles time vnto this day &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If you were as redy to proove, as you are to affirme things, then were your valour ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing worth. But you and the reſt, are ſo loth to be drawne to prooue yow miniſtry and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination by the word of God, that if you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not make vs take your word for the lawfullnes therof, then you will try by all means poſſible how you can get vs into ſome priſon, and keep vs there, vntill you haue founde your proofe out of ſome other darke corner: for by the light of Gods worde wee thinke you will never be able to proue the lawfullnes thereof.</p>
               <p>Theſe things that you ſay, have indeed been often by others affirmed: but never otherwiſe proved then by you at this preſent. But if you good ſir, would now take the payns to proue what you haue ſaide, by the word of God, your
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:177088:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>paines would deſerue thanks of many: And withall, let me intreat you ſir I pray you (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you ſay it hath had a continuall ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from the Apoſtles time vnto this daye) to ſhewe me, for my learning, which of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles was the <hi>Arch Apoſtle</hi> or <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> (If you pleaſe ſo to call him) ouer or before all the reſt, and from whom (or by what authority) he had that high place and Lordly office. And alſo where, and with whom he left that his <hi>Arch-Metropolitane</hi> authoritie to lord it over the reſt, as theſe do at this day, as you ſay.</p>
               <p>I profeſſe vnfainedly, that if I could ſee theſe things proved by the word of God, I would ſoon (through Gods mercy) change my minde.</p>
               <p>But in the meane time, to let paſſe the reſt of that frothie ſtuffe, which might be raked together in theſe your 7 and 8 Demands, I will come again to your 7 demand, though I could from the 16.17.18. and 19. lines in your 8 Demand light you ſuch a candle as I think you would be loath that any ſhould ſee the light thereof, but I will not blow at that cole now, yet you (againſt your will I am ſure) haue made a fayre beginning to kindle it, where you ſay thus, <hi>The Pope was not Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt before he had gotten the title of vniverſall Biſhop, nor compleat vntill he had gotten into his bands both ſwords, that is, both Civill and Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Dominion:</hi> if I ſhould now add but a little of your owne fuell to that coale, theſe your words would diſcover a great part of the miſtery of iniquity which growes in your mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry at this day. But to let that paſſe, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing doubting but God in his good time, by
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:177088:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>the brightnes of the Goſpel, wil cauſe the ſame to appear more and more dayly, I will come to your 7 Demand, where you tell vs of the Goſpell ſoundly and ſubſtantially taught and profeſſed: and the ſacraments ſo rightly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred and received in your Church, as for proportion no country in the world (you ſay) nor Nationall Church whatſoever, can affoord the like, &amp;c</p>
               <p>The like vaine boaſt of all the grounds of Chriſtian religion, ſoundly held and profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, &amp;c. I met with in your third Demand: but neither there nor heare you ſpeake any word of the practiſe, Chriſtian religion, and of the kingly power and office of Chriſt gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning your Church: of theſe things you ſay nothing: nothing how Chriſt ought to reigne as King in his Church, by his owne Lawes and ordinances executed, and adminiſtred in and by his owne offices and officers which he hath given unto and appointed in his Church forthat worke, Ephe. 4.11.12.13. Rom. 12.6.7.8.9. Not a word of this, I pray you Sir, let not this candle be light, howſoever you do: you may make your people think that Chriſt will be a Prophet to teach them, and a Prieſt to ſacrifice for them, though he be not a King to rule and reigne over them in and by his owne Lawes and officers: they perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture know not (or dare not tell you) that this is a denying of apart of the mediatorſhip of Chriſt: therefore Sir, as long as you can, let them not know the kingly office of Chriſt, nor what the Holy Ghoſt ſaith in Luk. 19.27. let them know no other government, for the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:177088:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>Church but your ſpitituall courts: it wil ſerue their turne well enough, untill the Lord ſhall moue their harts better to conſider and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the truth of his will reveiled in his word, which in his good time he will do unto all thoſe that earneſtly deſire, and with upright harts ſeeke and labour to worſhip and ſerue him in ſpirit and in truth. And now I will labour to ſhew the deceit of your vainglory in boaſting of the word and ſacraments, which you ſay are ſo ſoundly taught and admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>You would haue us (and all men) take it for granted that the nation of England is the true viſible Church of Chriſt: which you are not able to proue: then you go on, telling us of the ſound and ſubſtantiall things in this your Church: but we would firſt intreat you to ſhew us your Church conſtituted and buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded according to the ſcripture: if your Church be as you would make us beleue, then ſhew it, that we may ſee and diſcerne whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be ſoundly and ſubſtantially built of choyſe trees, and of pretious living ſtones (to the beſt of mans diſcerning) hewed and ſquared and faſtned together according to the heavenly patterne: every ſtone living, elect and pretious: (I ſay ſtill in the beſt of mans diſcerning) every ſtone hauing his beauty, his burden and order: all of them laboring to ſupport one another, to edifie one another, to exhort, to admoniſh and reproue one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that ſo they may be the habitation of God, as theſe ſcriptures do ſhew, Exo. 19.5.6. and chap. 25.8.9, 40. 1. Chro. 29.2. Zach.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:177088:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>14.21. compared with Heb. 8.1.2.5.6. &amp;c. Chap. 9.11.14.1. Pet. 2.4.5.7.8.9. Act. 2.37.41.42. Rev. 1.5.6, Heb. 3.13. Chap. 10.24.15. Lev. 19.17. Gala. 6.1 2. with many other, which I omit.</p>
               <p>The materiall Temple (which was but a tipe of this) we read to be built from the very foundation: of choiſe coſtly perfect ſtones: the beames and rafters of choiſe <hi>Ceaders, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gummim trees,</hi> 1. King. 5.17. Chap. 6.7. 2. Chro. 2.8. Ezra. 3.7.12. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But of the incomparable beauty and unut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terable excellency of this ſpirituall Temple<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> under the holy miniſtry &amp; happy government of Chriſt, it muſt be ſuch as none may grow nor be planted there, untill they be firſt cut off from their corrupt naturall ſtock where they grew before: and then be grafted into the true oliue tree, the true vine: yea and being plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ingrafted, that plant, that branch that bringeth not forth good fruit, but bringeth forth evill fruit apparantly ſeene and known, muſt be cut of and caſt out, Rom. 11.17.18.19.20.21. 1. Cor. 6.11. Tit. 3.3. &amp;c. Rom. 6.4.5.6. &amp;c. Math. 3.10. and 7.19. and 15.13. Luk. 13.6. Ioh. 15.6. Math. 18.15.16.17. Rom. 16.17.18. 1. Cor. 5.11.12.13. Now ſhew us your Church to be thus built, and thus ordered according to the teſtament of Chriſt: I doe not meane thus built in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect maner: but that every member of your Church in the plating thereof do in the beſt of mans diſcerning, according to Godly iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in his or their meaſure, hewen, fitted and ſquared for the building, before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e be
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:177088:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>faſtned there into: for as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>We which liue, muſt no more liue unto our ſelues, but unto the will of him that dyed for us and roſe againe: Ephe.</hi> 4.22.23.24. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.15.17. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.3. <hi>We muſt be new creatures, for we are the workmanſhip of God created anew into Chriſt Ieſus unto good works, which God hath ordayned that we ſhould walk in them, Ephe.</hi> 2.10.</p>
               <p>When you haue proved (and ſhewed us) your Church thus framed, faſhioned, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, then we wil take a view of thoſe things which you ſay (but you proue not) to be, therein ſo ſound and ſubſtantially taught and adminiſtred.</p>
               <p>But if you ſtill boaſt of thoſe good things in your Church, and yet your Church it ſelfe be built of rough tree, or rotten timber, hay and ſtubble, or of the thorns and bryers of the wildernes, and with ſuch dead or hard ſtones as cannot be hewen and ſquared, and faſtned into the building together, according to the heavenly prtterne, then is your Church a falſe Church, and deceitfull, notwithſtanding all your ſound and ſubſtantiall things therein: which things although they be (indeed) both ſound and ſubſtantiall of themſelues, yet will they not keep up your tottering building but in time it will fall and come to naught. And this at this time ſhall ſerue for anſwer to your 7 and 8 Demands: only thus much more: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I would not haue you any more boaſt, or go about to daſell our eyes with the ſight of thoſe things which you ſay are in your Church, untill you haue ſhewed us the true forme and faſhion of the building of your
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:177088:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>Church, I will demand of you this one que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion;</p>
               <p>When the Prophet <hi>Haggai,</hi> chap. 1. reproved the Iewes for that Gods houſe was not builded among them: would it haue been a ſufficient anſwer for them, thinke you Sir, to haue ſaid to the Prophet thus, Wee haue coſtly and faire, ſound and ſubſtantiall ſeelings of the ſweeteſt and pureſt wood, coſtly carved and curiouſly wrought, with many goodly and rich hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, cuſhings, carpets, and curtins, with ſo many other coſtly and ſumptuous ornaments and deckings, yea all whatſoever, according to the appointment of the law for Gods houſe, as for the proportio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, no Countrey in the world can afford the like. Nay Sir, admit they ſhould alſo haue ſaid thus. And behold alſo, we haue the foundation layd, and we haue many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert and excellent builders, all of them ſound and learned workmen: and for inſtruments, alſo, to hew and ſquare the timber and ſtone, we haue ſo good as non can be better: of which timber and ſtones alſo we haue ſo great plenty, and ſo excellent good, with all other things neceſſary to finiſh the building, as for proportio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no country in the world can afford the like: therefore although the ſtones be neither layd, nor ſquared, nor the timber hewed, fitted nor framed: yet haue we the houſe of God well builded.</p>
               <p>What think you Sir, would this haue been a ſufficient anſwer to haue ſatiſfied the prophet? if no, conſider then how little your vaine boaſt will ſtand you in ſtead in the day of your appearing: ſearch the Scriptures, and you ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:177088:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>find there, that every true viſible Church of Chriſt muſt conſiſt of a company of people (be they many or few) that are called out and ſeparated from the froward generation of the world, by the Goſpell, (<hi>Iohn.</hi> 15.19. 17.6.9.11.14, <hi>&amp;c. Act.</hi> 2.40. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.15 16.17.18.) and ioyned (or built) together into a holy communion and fellowſhip, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelues, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.41.44. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 2.13.19.20.22.) all of them being (in their mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure beleevers, pricked in their harts for their ſinnes, and now laboring together to continue in the Apoſtles doctrine, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.27.42.</p>
               <p>Being thus coupled and knit together they are called in the Scripture <hi>the Temple of God,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.16.17. <hi>the habitation of God, Ephe.</hi> 2.22. <hi>the Church of God,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor</hi> 1.2.2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. unto the which <hi>Church he daly addeth thoſe that he will ſaue, Act.</hi> 2.41.47. they are then called, <hi>Saints, Rom.</hi> 1.7. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.2. they are called <hi>Holy Bretheren. Heb.</hi> 3.1. they are called <hi>the body of Chriſt, and members for their part of the whole building of God.</hi> Conſider what is ſaid, &amp;c. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.7. &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="9">9 Demand. And now to your Counter-Demand, which is: <hi>Whether any new lawes can or ought to be made, or inacted: or any further reformation made without the chriſtian Princes or Magiſtrats conſent, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9 <hi>Anſwer.</hi> I Anſwer no. And I further ad, that whatſoever ſubiects, of what degree or ſtate ſoever they be, that ſhall go about either to inact any new lawes in the Kings Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or to reforme the order and ſtate of the Kingdome, contrary to that order which is
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:177088:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>already eſtabliſhed, without the conſent and lawfull authority of the Prince &amp; Magiſtrate, he is by the word of God iudged and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned worthy of damnation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.12. 5.6. <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.18.19. And if for this his or their offence, the Prince and Magiſtrats do put him or them to death (as by their lawfull an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority they may) it is no more then they haue iuſtly and worthily deſerved for their evill doings.</p>
               <p>The next word in this your 9 Demand, are thus ſet downe, and thus odly pointed, <hi>or ever in a well ordered Church hath bin inacted, or made and whether, they haue done well, to ſeparate with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Kings Maieſties leaue and licence, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the ſtate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe your refined words, as they be in this faſhion ſet downe, I doe not well vnderſt and 2 therefore I will giue you no other anſwere then is already made in the former words: de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring that this which is heere anſwered may be compared with that which is written for anſwer to the laſt 4 lines of your ſecond De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and I think it will giue ſufficient ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction: and for the better cleering of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meanings: I will demand of you theſe two queſtions deſiring your anſwer, if not printed, yet under your hand writing.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 1. Whether Chriſt be not the only wiſe God and everlaſting King, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect law giver to his Church: and whether all Kings, Potentats, Princes and people be not bound to ſubmit themſelues as true and faithfull ſubiects unto him and to his lawes given unto his Church: or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:177088:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>any or all of them may by their royall power, learning or authority, alter, change, leaue out, or ad unto any of thoſe lawes which Chriſt hath already ſet forth in his laſt will and teſtament.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 2 Whether every particular man (and conſequently all men be not bound by the word of God to ſeparate themſelues from every knowne ſinne and error (whether in faith, or converſation of life) that the Lord ſhall giue him ſight of: and labor diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to reforme themſelues and their families according to the law and will of God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in his word, without the conſent of the Chriſtian Prince and Magiſtrates under whom hee liveth: or whether they bee bound to go on and continue ſtill in their ſinne or error, and not to ſeparate from the ſame untill they haue firſt ſued for, and obtained the Princes and Magiſtrats leaue and licence and conſent of the ſtate, that is indeed and breifly whether God muſt be, God or no, eexcept men will giue him leaue.</p>
               <p n="10">10 <hi>Demand.</hi> your tenth and laſt Demand is. <hi>Whether it were not the Separatists beſt courſe to returne againe to Gods true Church and people, from whom (you ſay) upon ſome conceited hard dealing they haue made an unlawfull rent, and there to confer with the beſt learned: and if ſtill their conſciences be ſomewhat tender, to ſupplicate for ſome favour and liberty: or if (ſay you) they will not take this courſe: whether it weare not good for them for the avoiding of ſcandill, and in expectance of ſome proſperous ſucceſſe by
<pb facs="tcp:177088:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>the permiſſion of our noble King and bonor able Counſell, to remoue to Virginea, and make a Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation there, in hope to convert infidels to christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Although I can partly geſſe in what humor you propounded this your Demand, yet I will not anſwer you according to that your humor, but I will anſwer you even as I deſire to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the truth in loue and peace with you and with all men.</p>
               <p>I anſwer, Thoſe that haue ſeparated and made an unlawful rent from Gods true Church and people (as you ſay) it is the beſt courſe for them to returne againe, and with godly ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row to manifeſt their true and unfained repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance for the unlawfull rent they haue made.</p>
               <p>And that this may be the ſooner effected and brought to paſſe: ſeeing that you ſtill take it for granted that your Nationall Church, and Pariſh-Aſſemblies of England, is the true viſible Church of Chriſt: I do once againe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat you to ſhew vs the true forme and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion of your Church: And lay you apart all wrath and Envious Anger, that ſo we may to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in peace and love: you with us, and we with you, take a view and conſider of your Church, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pare the form &amp; faſhion therof with the forme and faſſion of the true viſible Church of Chriſt, as it is deſcribed vnto us in the ſcripture: If you can proue your Church or pariſh aſſemblies to be like vnto that true viſible Church of Chriſt both for true matter whereof it is built, viz. <hi>Saints:</hi> And alſo for the maner of the building, beeing coupled and combined according to the heavenly pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern.
<pb facs="tcp:177088:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>Both you and all men ſhall ſee, that I am willing, not onely to returne againe, but alſo to labour with godly diligence, to live in a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly communion and fellowſhipe with you, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boring to obey the lawes and ordinances of our Lord and Saviour Ieſus Chriſt, ſupporting and ſtrengthning one another in all loue: And if this good and godly courſe maye be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed: not onely I my ſelfe, but all of vs, that now are ſeparated from you, would much more willingly and gladly returne againe and labor to plant our ſelues againe in the meaneſt parte of England, to inioy peace with holineſſe and to follow the truth in loue among our kindred and friends in our owne natiue cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, then either to continue where now many of vs as yet liue, or to plant our ſelues in Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginia or in any other country in the world, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon any conditions, or hope of any thing in this lyfe whatſoeuer. Yet euen for <hi>Virginia</hi> thus much, When ſome of ours deſired to haue pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted our ſelues there, with his majeſties leaue upon theſe three grounds, firſt, that they might be means of replanting the goſpel amongſt the heathens. Secondly that they might liue vnder the Kings government. Thirdly, that they might make way for, and unite with others, what in them lieth, whoſe conſciences are greived with the ſtate of the Church in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land: the Byſhops did by all means oppoſe them, and their friends therein; and though they, aboue other men, pretend the planting of the Goſpell amongſt heathens, as you here do, yet haue they been rather content, that the moſt vile miſcreants in the kingdom and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:177088:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſuch as were rather like to turne chriſtians to heathens then to make of heathens Chriſtians, then they.</p>
               <p>And thus much for anſwer to your ten Counter Demaunds: nothing doubting but we ſhall be able to beare the waight of your next blow with patience, when it comes forth. If in the meane tyme I haue not anſwered you to any or all theſe your demands as you deſire, yet I haue endevoured my ſelfe to do it accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to truth in the beſt of my vnderſtanding, as the word of God hath directed me.</p>
               <p>I doe intreat you ſir, not to ſuffer the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduiſed anger of your owne evill and froward hart, cauſe you to take things in the worſt part; although I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe that at the firſt ſight, or view hereof, this my harſh, rude, and vnlearned writing may ſeeme vnpleaſant and offenſiue: yet vppon better and more ſerious conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons you ſhall haue leſſe cauſe to find fault.</p>
               <p>Therfore ſir, When you finde heerein any thing that may moue you to take offence, I pray you paſſe by it in loue, &amp; ſhew you forth that godly patience, which you ſomtime teach to others. Remember ſir, <hi>He that is ſlow to wrath, is of great wiſedome: but he that is of a haſtie minde exalteth folly, Pro.</hi> 14.29. <hi>And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, he that is ſlowe vnto anger is better then the mightie man: and he that ruleth his owne mynde is better then he that winneth a Citty. Pro,</hi> 16, 32.</p>
               <p>Conſider alſo, ſir, It is you that haue drawne me to write, and therefore you haue the leſſe cauſe to be angry, with me: except your hart be enuious, full of deceit &amp; malice, couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, pride, and vainglory, Rom. 1.29.30.31.
<pb facs="tcp:177088:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>againſt which things (co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering how euill they be in any) it may be hoped that you haue lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to ſtriue. Philip. 2.3. and doe labour to be purged from an evill conſcience, Heb. 10.21.22.23.24, I pray you ſir, beare with mee for writing thus vulearnedly: I haue endevoured my ſelfe in the beſt manner that I can, to ſpeake according to the word, as taught of the holy Ghoſt: from which, where I haue ſwarved, or abuſed the ſame, I humbly craue of you, &amp; of euery godly wiſe Reader, Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an correction, rather then pardon: for it ought to goe before, and ſhall be more profitable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me: yea greater every way ſhall the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit therof be, both for me, and for others alſo: for I being better inſtructed, ſhall through Gods mercy, both repent and learne to amend my faults; and others ſhall reape the fruits of Gods graces which more plentifully by your godly and diligent care, louingly to correct what you ſee amiſſe: vnto the which dutie of loue, if I may any way ſtir you and others vp, I ſhall not thinke my labour wholy loſt, but ſhall be very glad to ſee you and others ſo well affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. Fare yee well.</p>
               <p>Let all Glory and honor, praiſe and thankes be giuen to God alone.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:177088:24"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
